U. Roberto (Robin) Romano Papers 2008.0006
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
U. Roberto (Robin) Romano Papers
Bulk, 1996-2006
1972-2011
2008.0006
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
46.0 Linear feet
Research files and photography by noted photographer and documentary filmmaker U. Roberto (Robin) Romano, who has documented child labor in Brazil, India, Indonesia, Kenya, Nepal, and Pakistan, migrant farm labor in the United States and Mexico, and the cocoa industry in the Ivory Coast.
Romano, U. Roberto (Robin), 1958-
Biography
U. Roberto Romano (Robin) is a photographer, filmmaker and human rights educator. The son of the artist and Works Progress Administration (WPA) muralist Umberto Romano, Robin Romano was born in New York where he attended the Lycee Francais, Allen Stevenson School and Horace Mann High School. Mr. Romano graduated from Amherst College as an Interdisciplinary Scholar in 1980.
Romano began his career in documentaries as a producer and cameraman for Les Productions de Sagittaire in Montreal, where he worked on several series including 5 Defis and L'Oeil de L'Aigle.
His film projects include Death of a Slave Boy, a two-hour special shot in Pakistan for European broadcast, Globalization and Human Rights hosted by Charlayne Hunter Gault for PBS, Stolen Childhoods, the first theatrically released feature documentary on global child labor, The Dark Side of Chocolate, a feature documentary on trafficking in Western Africa, and The Harvest/La Cosecha, a feature documentary on child migrant laborers in the United States for which he won the Shine Global Award. He was also a contributor to the NPR and BBC specials on slavery in the Ivory Coast and has contributed to films as diverse as In Debt We Trust and Darfur Now.
As a still photograph, his exhibition "Stolen Childhoods: the Global Plague of Child Labor," was on view at the William Benton Museum of Fine Art at the University of Connecticut in 2006. He has been the photographer for Rugmark, a foundation working to end illegal child labor in the carpet industry and to offer educational opportunities to children in South Asia. Additionally, Romano created the mural and poster for the Council on Foreign Relations announcing their universal education campaign. Other organizations that have used his work include Human Rights Watch, Amnesty International, Free the Slaves, The International Labor Organization, Stop the Traffik, The Hunger Project, International Labor Rights Forum, The Farm Labor Organizing Committee and Antislavery International. His work has appeared in such publications as The Ford Foundation Quarterly, The Stanford Review, Scholastic, and UConn Magazine, and has been seen on billboards and posters around the world. Romano has appeared as a guest on Nightline with Ted Koppel as well as Newsnight with Aaron Brown.
As an advocate for and an authority on children's and human rights, Romano has appeared at many forums, schools and universities. He gave the Frank Porter Graham Lecture at the Johnson Center for Academic Excellence, University of North Carolina, and the Gene and Georgia Mittelman Distinguished Lecture in the Arts at the University of Connecticut. In 2007 he was invited to give the plenary speech at the Association of Farmworker Opportunity Programs annual conference in Coeur d'Alene. He has also lectured at the Rhode Island School of Design and the Oak Institute for International Human Rights at Colby College.
As an educator, Romano has taught graduate level courses at both New York University and Columbia University, where he continues his membership in the Columbia University Seminar on Globalization, Labor and Popular Struggles.
The most current information regarding Mr. Romano's activities and career can be found on his website
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series:
Series I: Child Labor, arranged alphabetically by subject; includes In the Best Interests of Children and Stolen Childhoods.
Series II: The Dark Side of Choclolate, arranged alphabetically by subject.
Series III: Migrant Labor, arranged alphabetically by subject; includes The Harvest.
Series IV: Human Rights, arranged alphabetically by subject; includes Children in the Crossfire, An Indifferent World, and The Hunger Project.
Series V: Administrative, arranged alphabetically by subject.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains photographs, negatives, newspaper and magazine clippings, notes, administrative records, publications, pamphlets, correspondence, optical and magnetic disks, moving images, and posters relating to Romano’s activities in human rights. Entries titled “research” contain clippings related to the subject indicated.
A number of projects are represented in the collection including Stolen Childhoods, The Dark Side of Chocolate, The Harvest, The Hunger Project, Children in the Crossfire, In the Best Interests of Children, and An Indifferent World. Subjects include child labor, migrant workers, fair trade, human trafficking, and other human rights issues. The collection covers many areas of the world including the United States, Mexico, Brazil, Kenya, the Ivory Coast, Mali, Pakistan, India, Indonesia, Nepal, and Thailand.
Provenance and Acquisition
Over two hundred digital images and thirty-four framed photographic prints were donated by Mr. Romano in 2008/2009. Additional materials were transferred in 2011-2012 and are on deposit.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Separated Materials
The following materials have been separated from the collection and catalogued: Child Labour programmes Dodd A10506 Elimination of Child Labor Dodd A10505 Floods despite dams Dodd C11029 Child Labor in India Dodd A10522 Children in the Fields Dodd DVD 57 Stolen Childhoods Dodd VHS Scream: Stop Child Labor: Protection of Children Dodd A6068 Forced to Plough: Bonded Labour in Nepal's Agricultural Economy Dodd A10523 The Global Transformation Reader: An Introduction to the Globalization Debates Dodd Dragons in Distress: Asia's Miracle Economies in Crisis Dodd Media Democracy in Action's Censored 2006: The Top 25 Censored Stories Dodd Media Democracy in Action's Censored 2008: The Top 25 Censored Stores of 2006-2007 Dodd Enslaved People in 1990s: A Report by Anti-Slavery International Dodd The Child and the State in India Dodd A10517 Slavery in Brazil: A Link in the Chain of Modernization Dodd A7274 A Human Rights Message Dodd A10521 Children of Native America Today Dodd C10836 Ser Vecinos, con las Sabias Palabras de Fred Rogers Dodd A10516 Hearings on the East Timor Question 1998 Dodd Child Labour in Nepal Dodd A10515 Globalization Culture and Education in the New Millenium Dodd A10527 Child Labour in India Dodd A10522 Childern in War: A Guide to the Provision of Services: A Study for UNICEF Dodd C10838 Out of the Shadows Dodd State of the World's Children 2001
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to human rights issues and the work of photojournalists. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Romano, U. Roberto (Robin), 1958-; Civil actions.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Correspondence.; Human Rights; Interviews.; Notes.; Photographs.
- Series I: Child Labor, 1989-2010
  Scope and Content Note
  This series includes photographs, negatives, clippings, notes, publications, pamphlets, correspondence, optical and magnetic disks, moving images, and posters relating to child labor. Material for Stolen Childhoods and In the Best Interests of Children are included here. Countries covered include Brazil, India, Indonesia, Kenya, Mexico, Nepal, Pakistan, and the United States.
  - Digital photographs (original transfer)
  - Achmad Marzuki Interview Transcript, undated (Box 19, Folder 50)
  - Benton Museum of Fine Art at the University of Connecticut Exhibit, 2009; 10 oversized photographs (Oversize OS, Box 19, Folder 29)
  - Benton/UConn Contact Sheets, undated (Box 19, Folder 28)
  - BU Rugmark (empty), undated (Box 15, Folder 37)
  - Casa Alianza, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Casa Alianza Correspondence, 2002 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Child Labor, 1998-2001 (Box 24, Folder 116, Box 25, Folder 164, Folder 165, Folder 160)
  - Child Labor BG to be filed, 1996-2001 (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - Child Labor Coalition NCL, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 27)
  - Child Labor Film Interview, 2003 (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - Child Labor General, 2002-2004 (Box 24, Folder 119)
  - Child Labor Handbook, undated (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Child Labor Newsletter, 2002-2004 (Box 24, Folder 120, Folder 121)
  - Child Labor Project Grant, 2001 (Box 19, Folder 47)
  - Child Labor Resource Guide, undated (Box 20, Folder 41)
  - Childhood Under Threat, 2005 (Box 20, Folder 34)
  - Chrome Lasers, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Other Pakistan)
  - Convention on the Rights of the Child, undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 2004-2007 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Department of Labor Project, 2000 (Box 19, Folder 55)
  - Documenting NGO Good Practices, undated (Box 25, Folder 166)
  - Ford Foundation, 2001 (Box 19, Folder 43, Box 15, Folder 26)
  - Global March Against Child Labor, 1998-2002 (Box 24, Folder 152, Folder 153, Box 19, Folder 48)
  - Global March Images, Flyers, etc., 2003 (Box 15, Folder 24)
  - Global March Website, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - Global Movement for Children, undated (Box 24, Folder 127)
  - Guidelines, Questionnaire, and Outlines, undated (Box 22, Folder 23)
  - Haiti, 1999-2000 (Box 20, Folder 25)
  - HCO, undated (Box 25, Folder 157)
  - Helping Hands or Shackled Lives, 2004 (Box 24, Folder 126)
  - In the Best Interests of Children, 1995-2002
    - Correspondence, 1999 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Index, undated (Box 24, Folder 132)
    - Section 1, 2000 (Box 24, Folder 133)
    - Sections 2-7, 2000 (Box 24, Folder 134)
    - Section 8, undated (Box 24, Folder 135)
    - Sections 9-10, 1999 (Box 24, Folder 136)
    - Section 11, undated (Box 24, Folder 137)
    - Section 12, undated (Box 24, Folder 138)
    - Section 13, undated (Box 24, Folder 139)
    - Section 14, 1998 (Box 24, Folder 140)
    - Section 15, undated (Box 24, Folder 141)
    - Section 16, 1998-1999 (Box 24, Folder 142)
    - Section 18, undated (Box 24, Folder 143)
    - Section 19, 1998 (Box 24, Folder 144)
    - Sections 20-22, undated, 1995 (Box 24, Folder 145)
    - Sections 23-25, 1998-1999 (Box 24, Folder 146)
    - Section 26, 1997 (Box 24, Folder 147)
    - Sections 27-34, 1995-2000 (Box 24, Folder 148)
    - Sections 35-40, 1999-2000 (Box 24, Folder 149)
    - Section 41, 1999 (Box 24, Folder 150)
    - India Country Report, 2000 (Box 19, Folder 22)
    - International LaborRights Fund (ILRF)/In the Best Interests of Children, undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Kenya Background Country Report, 2000 (Box 19, Folder 53)
    - Labels, undated (Box 19, Folder 56)
    - Memos, 1999 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Mexico, 1999-2002 (Box 25, Folder 191)
    - Negatives, Bulk, 2000; 1999-2004 (Box 2, Other India Train Kids/Ruchika Selects SC, Box 1, Other Indonesia Bekasi Selects - SC, Box 9, Other India Color - SC, Other India - Gravel Quarry, Other India Assorted, Box 3, Other India B&W - SC, Other India Brick Kiln Selects SC)
    - Optical Disks (12), 2001-2002 (Box 11)
    - Photographs (39), 2000 (Box 1, Other India - Gravel Quarry)
    - Production Material, undated (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Proposal for Funding, 2000 (Box 24, Folder 131)
  - India Research, 1998-2005 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - International Conference on "Out of Work and Into School,", 2004 (Box 20, Folder 42)
  - International Labor Office (ILO), undated, 1998 (Box 25, Folder 162, Folder 163, Folder 161)
  - ILO International Program on the Elimination of Child Labour (IPEC) Documents, 2001 (Box 24, Folder 129, Folder 128)
  - ILO Press Releases, 1999 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - ILO Publications, undated (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - ILO Tokyo Exhibit, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Journal Articles, 1999 (Box 24, Folder 114)
  - Moving Images (12), 1994-2003 (Box 5, Box 6)
  - Negatives, 1996 (Box 7, Other Pakistan 1996 B&W (0130-0202))
  - NGO Position on ILO Convention 182 and U.S. Law, undated (Box 20, Folder 35)
  - Notes, undated, 1999 (Box 20, Folder 19, Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Optical Discs (21), 2000-2007 (Box 11)
  - Photograph List for International Labor Rights Forum, 2001 (Box 19, Folder 24)
  - Policy Lessons from Development and Implementation of Child Labor, 2010 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Questions for Senator Harkin on Child Labor, undated (Box 22, Folder 24)
  - Research, 1998-2008 (Box 19, Folder 1, Folder 25, Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Report: A Future Without Child Labor, 2002 (Box 24, Folder 118, Folder 117)
  - Report and Article, undated (Box 24, Folder 125)
  - Report and Copy of Book, undated (Box 24, Folder 123)
  - Romano Photography Speeches, 2008 (Box 19, Folder 32)
  - Rugmark, 1993-2007 (Box 19, Folder 27, Box 25, Folder 159)
  - Rugmark Faces of Freedom Photo Exhibit, 2008-2009 (Box 6, Folder 1, Folder 3)
  - Rugmark Photo Library Index, 2000 (Box 19, Folder 42)
  - Rugmark Publicity, 2001 (Box 20, Folder 47)
  - Scholastic News, 2000-2004 (Box 24, Folder 115)
  - Scholastic Tear Sheets, 2002 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Senator Tom Harkin, 1999-2003 (Box 16, Folder 18, Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Stolen Childhoods, Bulk, 2000-2003; 1995-2006
    - Ayers - Rondone, 2003-2005 (Box 19, Folder 18)
    - Bibro Unbroken Exhibit Documents, 2004 (Box 24, Folder 134)
    - Bolsa-Escola Research Project, undated, 2001-2002 (Box 19, Folder 64, Box 25, Folder 188)
    - Brazil, 2002 (Box 25, Folder 189)
    - Brazil Child Labor, 2001-2002 (Box 19, Folder 66)
    - Brazil Children in Drug Trafficking, 2002 (Box 20, Folder 17)
    - Brazil Negatives, 2002 (Box 1, Other Brazil Selects - SC, Box 7, Other Brazil B&W - SC, Other Brazil Color - SC)
    - Brazil Correspondence, 2002 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Brazil Research, 2001-2002 (Box 20, Folder 16)
    - BU Brazil, undated (Box 15, Folder 29)
    - BU Global March Shiska Yatra, undated (Box 15, Folder 43)
    - BU Himalayan Culture A. Wientraub, undated (Box 15, Folder 42)
    - BU India, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 39)
    - BU Indonesia Bekasi, undated (Box 15, Folder 40)
    - BU Indonesia Jermals, undated (Box 15, Folder 41)
    - BU Kenya, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - BU SC Selects, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 44)
    - Caption Information, 2005 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Child Labor in Coffee Industry, 2005 (Box 24, Folder 130)
    - Child Labor Interview List, undated (Box 22, Folder 22)
    - Children in Hazardous Work, Indonesia, 1995 (Box 23, Folder 83)
    - CNN Newsnight Transcript, 2004 (Box 20, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence, 2000-2004 (Box 22, Folder 7, Box 20, Folder 15, Folder 11)
    - Documents, 2002-2004 (Box 22, Folder 17, Folder 18, Folder 16)
    - Draft Script, undated (Box 19, Folder 68)
    - Exhibition Book, 2005 (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - Film Background Kenya, 2002 (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Film Interviews and IDs Kenya, 2002 (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Film Production Kenya, 2002 (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Film Promotional Materials, 2002 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Film SC, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 33)
    - Film Screening, undated (Box 22, Folder 25)
    - Film Scripts, undated (Box 22, Folder 30, Folder 28, Folder 27, Folder 31)
    - Film Scripts by Tape Numbers, undated (Box 22, Folder 30-51)
    - Film Scripts, September 9th Revision, 2003 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Film Scripts, September 11th Revision, 2003 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Film Scripts, September 25th Revision, 2003 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Galen Films Fundraising, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - India, 2000-2001 (Box 23, Folder 101, Folder 100, Folder 102, Folder 103)
    - India Negatives, Bulk, 2000; 2000-2004 (Box 3, Other India B&W - SC, Box 2, Other India Train Kids/Ruchika Selects SC, Other India Brick Kiln Selects SC, Box 9, Other India Color - SC)
    - India Brick Kiln Thumbnails, undated (Box 26, Folder 208)
    - India Brick Kiln and Gravel Quarry Children, undated (Box 19, Folder 60)
    - India Gravel Quarry Thumbnails, 2000 (Box 26, Folder 209)
    - India Photo Selection, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 30)
    - India Train Children Thumbnails, undated (Box 26, Folder 210)
    - Indonesia, 1999-2000 (Box 23, Folder 87, Folder 104, Folder 105)
    - Indonesia Negatives, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Other Indonesia Jermals B&W/Color SC, Box 1, Other Indonesia Bekasi Selects - SC)
    - Indonesia Case Study, undated (Box 23, Folder 110)
    - Indonesia Correspondence, 2002 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Indonesia Country Study, 1998 (Box 23, Folder 111)
    - Indonesia Dump, 2003 (Box 26, Folder 211)
    - Indonesia, Jermals, 2003 (Box 26, Folder 212)
    - India Miscellaneous, undated (Box 19, Folder 16)
    - Indonesia Photo thumbnails, undated (Box 15, Folder 31)
    - Indonesia: Reports, 1995 (Box 23, Folder 82)
    - Indonesia: Research Study, 2000 (Box 23, Folder 94)
    - Indonesia Selects, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 34)
    - International Labor Office (ILO) Funding, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - Iqbal Masih, undated (Box 19, Folder 26)
    - Jermal Tape Logs, undated (Box 20, Folder 23)
    - Journey of EDHI Foundation, undated (Box 20, Folder 24)
    - Kalish Satyarthi, 2003-2004 (Box 23, Folder 97)
    - Kenya, 1999-2002 (Box 22, Folder 81)
    - Kenya Negatives, 2002 (Box 1, Other Kenya Coffee/AIDS Selects - SC, Other Kenya Color - SC, Box 4, Other Kenya B&W - SC)
    - Kenya Background Documents, 1999-2002 (Box 23, Folder 79, Folder 77, Folder 78, Folder 75, Folder 76)
    - Kenya Coffee Children, undated (Box 19, Folder 59)
    - Kenya Coffee Plantation, 2002-2003 (Box 26, Folder 213, Box 23, Folder 73)
    - Kenya Correspondence, 2001-2002 (Box 23, Folder 74)
    - Kenya Notes, 2006 (Box 19, Folder 69)
    - Kenya Prints, undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Logbook, 2002 (Box 22, Folder 21)
    - Magnetic Disk, undated (Box 11, Other Indonesia)
    - Magnetic Disk, undated (Box 11, Disk ILRF/DOL)
    - Martha's Vineyard Indpendent Film Festival, 2003 (Box 19, Folder 36)
    - Media Advocates for Children, undated (Box 20, Folder 32)
    - Mexico Agriculture Thumbnails, undated (Box 26, Folder 215)
    - Mexico Background, undated, 2001-2004 (Box 16, Folder 24, Box 15, Folder 36)
    - Mexico Documents, 1999-2002 (Box 25, Folder 190)
    - Mexico Photo Thumbnails, undated (Box 15, Folder 32)
    - Mexico Texts, 2001-2003 (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - Moving Images (8), 2002-2004 (Box 5)
    - Negatives, 2003 (Box 4, Other Assorted To Sort)
    - Notes, undated (Box 19, Folder 35, Box 20, Folder 18)
    - Optical Disks (102), 2001-2006 (Box 11, Box 4, Box 2, Box 15)
    - Pablo's Story, undated (Box 19, Folder 65)
    - Pakistan, 1999 (Box 23, Folder 106)
    - Pakistan Negatives, 1996-1997 (Box 10, Other Pakistan 1997 Color (0532-8943), Other Pakistan 1996 Color (6168-7138))
    - Photo Essays, undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Photocopied publication written in an Asian language, undated (Box 19, Folder 70)
    - Photographs (513), 2000-2003 (Box 2, Other India Brick Kiln Selects SC - 2000, Box 1, Other Indonesia Bekasi Selects - SC - 2000, Box 3, Other Texas Selects - SC - 2003, Other India Train Kids/Ruchika Selects SC - 2000, Box 26, Folder 221, Other Kenya Coffee/AIDS Selects - SC - 2002, Other Brazil Selects - SC - 2002)
    - Photographs of Missed Cuts, undated (Box 26, Folder 216)
    - Press Kit, 2003 (Box 19, Folder 31)
    - Project Production, 2001-2002 (Box 19, Folder 58)
    - Rugmark, undated (Box 26, Folder 222)
    - Rugmark/ILRF, 2002 (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Rugmark: India, Pakistan and Nepal Photo Index, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Scholastic Correspondence, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Scholastic Web, 2003 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Scripts from the Oprah Winfrey Show Segment, 2004 (Box 22, Folder 26)
    - Soros BS, undated (Box 19, Folder 30)
    - Stolen Childhoods: A Feature Documentary Proposal for Funding, 2002 (Box 4)
    - Street Children Thumbnails, undated (Box 26, Folder 214)
    - Teacher Resource Guide, 2006 (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - Test Prints for Shows and Banners, undated (Box 26, Folder 220)
    - Texas Negatives, 2003 (Box 3, Other Texas Selects - SC, Other Texas B&W/Color - SC)
    - Thank You List, undated (Box 22, Folder 29)
    - Thumbnails, undated (Box 26, Folder 219)
    - Thumbnails of Missed Cuts, undated (Box 26, Folder 217, Folder 218)
    - Transcripts by Characters, undated (Box 22, Folder 52)
    - Transcripts: Marihot Gultom, undated (Box 22, Folder 67, Folder 66, Folder 53)
    - Transcripts: Irwanto, undated (Box 22, Folder 64)
    - Transcripts: N.P. Joseph, undated (Box 22, Folder 55)
    - Transcripts: Kailash, undated (Box 22, Folder 56, Folder 69)
    - Transcripts: Kapilanandmond, undated (Box 22, Folder 62)
    - Transcripts: Inderjit Khurana, undated (Box 22, Folder 71)
    - Transcripts: Kumar, undated (Box 22, Folder 58)
    - Transcripts: Mohadi, undated (Box 22, Folder 65)
    - Transcripts: Basu Munti, undated (Box 22, Folder 54)
    - Transcripts: Rajesh, undated (Box 22, Folder 57)
    - Transcripts: Ramaswamy, undated (Box 22, Folder 59)
    - Transcripts: Raneka, undated (Box 22, Folder 60)
    - Transcripts: Ruchika, undated (Box 22, Folder 61)
    - Transcripts: Sofyan Tan, undated (Box 22, Folder 68)
    - Transcripts: Zia Ul-Haque, undated (Box 22, Folder 63)
    - Transcripts: Richard Young, undated (Box 22, Folder 70)
    - United Nations Association Film Festival, 2003 (Box 19, Folder 17, Folder 21, Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Yatra Negatives, 2001 (Box 3, Other Yatra Color - SC, Other Yatra B&W - SC)
  - Street Children, Time for Kids, 2003 (Box 24, Folder 122)
  - The Convention on the Rights of the Child, 1989-1999 (Box 24, Folder 113)
  - The Hague Global Child Labor Conference, 2010 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - US/Mexico Child Labor Budget, 2000 (Box 19, Folder 49)
  - Vietnam, 2002 (Box 23, Folder 107)
  - Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, 2009-2010 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - 34 framed photographic prints of child labor from India, Indonesia, Kenya, Pakistan, Mexico, and the United States, 1999-2006
- Series II: The Dark Side of Chocolate, 2000-2010
  This series includes photographs, negatives, clippings, notes, publications, pamphlets, correspondence, optical and magnetic disks, and moving images relating to human trafficking in the cocoa industry in the Ivory Coast and Mali. Material for the documentary The Dark Side of Chocolate is included here.
  - Building on Quicksand: The Global Compact, Democratic Governance and Nestle, 2004 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Chocolate, 2005-2010 (Box 16, Folder 22)
  - Chocolate Trade, 2004-2008 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Clean Contacts, 2005 (Box 20, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 2005-2010 (Box 21, Folder 1, Box 20, Folder 29, Box 16, Folder 15, Box 19)
  - Cote d'Ivoire Child Labor Survey, 2007 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Dark Side of Globalization Lecture, 2006 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - IC to File, 2006-2009 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Interview Transcripts, undated (Box 19, Folder 24)
  - Interviews and Background, 2005-2006 (Box 20, Folder 27)
  - Mittleman CCIPS, 2000-2006 (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - Mittelman Distinguished Lecture at the University of Connecticut, 2006 (Box 22, Folder 15, Box 20, Folder 43)
  - Nestle, undated (Box 21, Folder 6, Box 20, Folder 40)
  - Nestle Lawsuit, 2006 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Notes, undated (Box 17, Folder 5, Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Optical Disks (12), 2006 (Box 11, Box 14)
  - Research, 2001-2006 (Box 21, Folder 2, Box 20, Folder 28, Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Scripts, undated (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - Transcripts IC/Mali, 2005-2006 (Box 20, Folder 26)
- Series III: Migrant Labor, 1972-2011